Guide to the New-York Historical Society General Correspondence 1805-2024 (bulk, 1805-1982) NYHS-RG 2
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. General Correspondence, 1908-1982; 117.29 Linear feet in 282 document boxes and one oversize folder
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Peters, Harry T. (including reception on 2/27/1943) (Box 231, Folder 2)
    Concerns responses to invitations for Harry T. Peters' lecture, "New York as the Wood Engraver Saw It."
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Ph (Box 231, Folder 3)
    Concerns the cause to collect funds for the rebuilding of Philippine libraries following liberation after the war. Correspondents include the Philadelphia Museum of Art.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Pi (Box 231, Folder 4)
    Correspondents include Pierce & Scopes.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Pl (Box 231, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Po (Box 231, Folder 6)
    Concerns clipping of a protest by concerned citizens of Pound Ridge, NY to United Nations Headquarters Commission requesting that the United Nations not develop in the town. Correspondents include Dr. Arthur Pound.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Polish Organizations & Individuals (Box 231, Folder 7)
    Correspondents include the Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America and Polish Roman Catholic Union of America.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Pool, Dr. Eugene H. (Box 231, Folder 8)
    Concerns Pool's gifts to the Society and his loans, including model of "Chesapeake" from the collection of Captain James Lawrence.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Poor, Walter Stone (Box 231, Folder 9)
    Concerns Walter S. Pool's donations to the Society.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Pr (Box 231, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Pray, Josephine D. (Mrs. Frank M. Pray) (Box 231, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Princeton University (Box 231, Folder 12)
    Concerns purchases made by Princeton (under the pseudonym of "Nassau" at the Brinley sale); Correspondents include Julian P. Boyd (Librarian).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Pu (Box 231, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Publicity (Box 231, Folder 14)
    Consists of the promotion of N-YHS exhibitions, including paintings by John James Audubon, to various radio stations, publications, and schools.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Q (Box 231, Folder 15)
    Correspondents include Queens Borough Public Library and Queens University (Kingston, Canada).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Ra (Box 231, Folder 16)
    Concerns meeting announcements for the Railway and Locomotive Historical Society and a program bulletin for National Officers, of which Dorothy Barck (Librarian) and David Shelley (Curator) were guests of honor.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Re (2 folders) (Box 231, Folder 17-18)
    Concerns war demands for Recordak equipment and film orders placed by N-YHS.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Remington Rand Inc. (Box 231, Folder 19)
    Concerns estimates for factory rebuilding of typewriters and supply orders.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Rhode Island-- MISC. (Box 231, Folder 20)
    Concerns the study of the system employed by the N-YHS's Registrar by the Museum of Art Rhode Island School of Design.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Rhode Island Historical Society (Box 231, Folder 21)
    Concerns the raising of money for the purchase of the Ward Family papers by the Rhode Island Historical Society; Correspondents include William G. Roelker (Director).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Ri (Box 232, Folder 1)
    Correspondents include Ringling Bros. & Barnum and Bailey Circus.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Roa-Rog (Box 232, Folder 2)
    Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller and Ford A. Rockwell, Assistant Librarian (Hartford Public Library).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Robinson, Charles Larned (Box 232, Folder 3)
    Concerns Charles Larned Robinson's article for The Christian Science Monitor on early American apple parers and his gifts of apple parers to the N-YHS.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Robinson, Rev. Millard L. (Box 232, Folder 4)
    Rev. Millard L. Robinson was a member of the Board of Trustees.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Rochester, City of (Box 232, Folder 5)
    Concerns organizations and offices in Rochester, NY including Rochester Museum of Arts and Sciences (Arthur C. Parker) and the University of Rochester (John R. Russell, Librarian).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Roh-Roz (Box 232, Folder 6)
    Concerns N-YHS's request for a list of portraits of President Roosevelt at the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library in Hyde Park, NY and manuscripts relating to the Great Nine Partners and the presentation by Roosevelt of the Minutes of the Council of Appointments in 1925; Correspondents: Edgar B. Nixon (Acting Director) and Margaret L. Suckley (In Charge of Dutchess County Material).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Rollins College (Box 232, Folder 7)
    Correspondents include Hamilton Holt (President of Rollins College).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Romaine, Lawrence B. (Box 232, Folder 8)
    Lawrence B. Romaine was a rare book dealer based in Middleboro, Mass.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Rosenbach Company (Box 232, Folder 9)
    Concerns the request for manuscripts and other material by Sir Shane Leslie (cousin of Winston Churchill) for a memoir of Churchill's Grandfather, Leonard Jerome.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Rn-Ry (Box 232, Folder 10)
    Concerns Russian War Relief Greater New York Campaign.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sa (2 folders) (Box 232, Folder 11-12)
    Consists of Salmagundi Club meeting minutes held on May 7, 1943, which included two resolutions introduced by Judge Donoghue.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Saint (Box 232, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. St. Louis City Art Museum (Box 232, Folder 14)
    Concerns data collected by the City Art Museum for the N-YHS project, "Dictionary of Artists in America to 1860"; Correspondent: Odille D. Stewart (Librarian).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sawitzky, William (Box 232, Folder 15)
    Concerns manuscripts for Sawitzky's book on Ralph Earl, arrangements for typing the material, and other matters.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sch (Box 232, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. School Art League (Box 232, Folder 17)
    Concerns arranging with N-YHS for junior members of Art League to take part in a spring series of talks and tours of the museum's five exhibitions; Correspondent: Dorothy Thornton.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sc (except Sch) (Box 232, Folder 18)
    Correspondents include Scribner Book store.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Schermerhorn, E. Gilbert (Box 232, Folder 19)
    Consists of a response to Schermerhorn from Dorothy Barck (Librarian) describing the galleries of the museums and the portraits, maps, silver, furniture, and other materials on exhibit Illustrating the History of New York City from the Dutch Period.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Se (Box 233, Folder 1)
    Correspondents include Harold Seton and Seaman's Church Institute.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sh (Box 233, Folder 2)
    Concerns the Presidential flag designed at request of Roosevelt and the executive order establishing for the first time a legal definition of the President's coat of arms and his seal.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Si (Box 233, Folder 3)
    Concerns N-YHS's subscription to Fred Singleton's publication, 19th Century Peep Show.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sk-Sl (Box 233, Folder 4)
    Correspondents include Mrs. Roswell Skeel, Jr.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sm (Box 233, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sn-So (Box 233, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Society of Colonial Wars (Box 233, Folder 7)
    Concerns an exhibition of historic flags at N-YHS with cooperation from the Society of Colonial Wars and the Sons of the Revolution.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sons of the Revolution (Box 233, Folder 8)
    Concerns announcements on organization letterhead in regard to meetings; annual Flag Day celebration, and R.W. G. Vail (Director, N-YHS) guest speaking about the N-YHS exhibition, "Our G.I.'s in Seven Wars."
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sp-Squ (Box 233, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Special Libraries Association (Box 233, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sta (2 folders) (Box 233, Folder 11-12)
    Concerns the publication of a book covering the Grider Powder Horn drawings by the Standard Printing & Publishing Co.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Ste (Box 233, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Steamship Historical Society of America (Box 233, Folder 14)
    The N-YHS was a member of The Steamship Historical Society of America (Salem, MA). Concerns member dues and annual meeting announcements.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Stevens, B.F. & Brown, Ltd. (Box 233, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Stevens, Henry, Son & Stiles (Box 233, Folder 16)
    Henry Stevens, Sons & Stiles were booksellers and publishers. Consists of purchase orders made by the N-YHS.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Sti-Sto (Box 233, Folder 17)
    Concerns memorial service in honor of the late I.N. Phelps Stokes.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Str-Sty (Box 233, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Streeter, Thomas W. (Box 233, Folder 19)
    Thomas W. Streeter was a rare-book dealer and owner of one of the largest collections of Americana in the country. His collection included early books, pamphlets, and maps, with a concentration on Texas history and Western transportation, 1795-1845. Concerns reference requests and other matters. Correspondent: Oscar Wegelin (Bibliographer).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Su-Sz (Box 233, Folder 20)
    Concerns Mr. and Mrs. Jacob Lorillard portraits given by Herbert Schuyler Cammann and Lorillard genealogy; "The Mount Family" exhibition at the Suffolk Museum at Stony Brook, Long Island (N-YHS loaned picture, "Bargaining for a Horse").
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Ta (Box 234, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Te (Box 234, Folder 2)
    Correspondents include Edward H. Terry (Appraiser and book dealer) and The Mirabeau B. Lamar Library (University of Texas at Austin).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Tempest, Ted (Box 234, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1943-1944. Thor Thors Reception 2/6/44 (Box 234, Folder 4)
    Concerns lecture and reception given on "Iceland, A Small Nation in a Great War," by Thor Thors; consists mainly of responses of attendance to the lecture.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Th (Box 234, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Ti-To (Box 234, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Tr-Ts (Box 234, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Tu-Ty (Box 234, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. U (Box 234, Folder 9)
    Correspondents include Union League Club (Margaret E. Lippincott, Librarian) and Dixon Ryan Fox (President, Union College).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. U.S.A. (2 folders) (Box 234, Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. U.S.A.-- Library of Congress (Box 234, Folder 12)
    Correspondents include Luther H. Evans (Librarian of Congress), St. George L. Sioussat (Chief, Division of Manuscripts), and Alice H. Lerch (Chief Bibliographer).
  - Correspondence 1944-1945. U.S.A.-- MISC. (Box 234, Folder 13)
    Correspondents include Major General Thomas B. Larkin, Commanding Second Service Command (Headquarter's, Governor's Island), Office of War Information, and United States Military Academy (Lt. Colonel W.J.Morton, F.A., Librarian).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. U.S.A.-- National Archives (Box 234, Folder 14)
    Concerns General Horatio Gates materials held at the National Archives.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. U.S.A.-- Navy Department/Naval Academy (Box 234, Folder 15)
    Concerns the N-YHS reaching out to Naval officers to strengthen its library and museum collections relating to United States Navy history with the addition of WWII materials.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. U.S.A.-- Smithsonian Institution (Box 235, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. U.S.A.--Treasury Department (Box 235, Folder 2)
    Concerns the issuing of War Bonds to finance the war effort, in particular the Seventh War Loan and Third War Loan Drives; distribution of materials to employees at N-YHS about the war loans.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. U.S.A.-- Victory Tax (Box 235, Folder 3)
    Concerns Tax Form 990: Annual Return of Organization Exempt from Income Tax for calendar years 1944-1945; includes instructions for Return of Victory Tax Withheld.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. U.S.A.-- "Wings over Central Pacific" Exhibition (Box 235, Folder 4)
    Concerns attendance for "Wings over the Central Pacific," an exhibition telling the story of the advance of the 7th Bomber Command across the Pacific that traveled to other parts of the country including Rochester (Museum of Arts and Sciences); loans to N-YHS for the exhibition.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. U.S.A.-- War Department, "E" Awards (B.C.Landauer Collection) (2 folders) (Box 235, Folder 5-6)
    Concerns Bella Landauer's request to the War Department for the Army-Navy "E" production award with the intention to add to the Bella Landauer Business Collection. This award was given to manufacturers of war materials for excellence; includes many press releases announcing names of producers of war materials which received this award, as well as invitations to a special exhibition of these printed programs of the Army-Navy "E" Awards to American Industries.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. U.S.A.-- War Production Board (Box 235, Folder 7)
    Consists of applications from N-YHS for priority assistance for the purchase of emulsion paper, photographic film, and other supplies to complete reproduction orders for the O.W.I. (Office of War Information) and other government departments, institutions, and scholars. Includes instructions on how to fill out the form.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. University Microfilms (Box 235, Folder 8)
    Concerns orders for microfilming periodicals in the N-YHS's collections.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Va-Vaz (Box 235, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Vail, R.W.G. (Box 235, Folder 10)
    Concerns personal correspondence exchanged between R.W.G. Vail (Director, N-YHS) and others, including N-YHS staff members Dorothy Barck (Librarian) and Donald A. Shelley (Curator of Paintings). Includes Vail's Pistol License Application for the protection from theft of the museum's valuable collections, and an article, "The Society Welcomes a New Director," which describes Vail succeeding A.J.Wall as Director of the N-YHS and his biography, written by member LeRoy E. Kimball.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Van Alstyne, William T. (Box 235, Folder 11)
    Concerns Treasurer's Monthly Report listing various income allottment for museum needs and general expenses.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Van Rensselaer, Kiliaen (Box 235, Folder 12)
    Concerns Van Rensselaer's publication, The Van Rensselaers of Rensselaerwyck.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Ve (Box 235, Folder 13)
    Correspondents include Mr. and Mrs. Bayard Verplanck.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Vi (Box 236, Folder 1)
    Concerns N-YHS subscription to The Villager newspaper.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Virginia Historical Society/State Library (Box 236, Folder 2)
    Correspondent: Alexander W. Weddell (President).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Vo-Vu (Box 236, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Von Hagen, Victor Wolfgang (Box 236, Folder 4)
    Concerns explorer and anthropologist von Hagen's research and other matters related to his publications F.Catherwood 1799-1854 - Architect-Explorer of Two Worlds (1946) and John Lloyd Stephens.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wa-Wal (Box 236, Folder 5)
    Correspondents include The Walker Engraving Corporation.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wall, A.J.-- General (2 folders) (Box 236, Folder 6-7)
    Concerns professional correspondence between A.J.Wall (Director, N-YHS) and outside institutions and clubs he was a member of. Correspondents include the Salmagundi Club, Columbia University, Grand Jury Association of New York County, and the Inn at Buck Hill Falls.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wall, A.J.-- Personal (Box 236, Folder 8)
    Concerns A.J.Wall's listing in Who's Who in America and letters of condolences following his death.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wall, A.J. -- Buck Hill Falls (Box 236, Folder 9)
    Concerns estimating values of Buck Hills property by C.H. Crowe Insurance Company and other matters in regard to Walls' property.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wall, A.J. -- Condolence, 1944-1945 (Box 236, Folder 10)
    Concerns condolences to the Society on the passing of A.J. Wall from institutions including the Bibliographical Society of America and the American Library Association.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wall, A.J., Jr., 1944-1945 (Box 236, Folder 11)
    Concerns the financial renumeration given to Alexander J. Wall, Jr. from the N-YHS during his service in the army; birth announcements for son A.J.Wall III. Correspondents include Charlotte Rowell.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wan-Waz (Box 236, Folder 12)
    Concerns exchanges with Washington Square Neighbors in regard to establishing zonings law to limit height of buildings facing city parks.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Washington Irving Exhibition and Lecture (Box 236, Folder 13)
    Concerns the first in a series of lectures for the winter of 1944-1945, "The Age of Washington Irving," given by Van Wyck Brooks. Includes remarks and introduction of R. W.G. Vail as the new Director of the Society and address cards.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wea-Wek (Box 236, Folder 14)
    Correspondents include Harry B. Weiss (Department of Agriculture, State of New Jersey).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Weekes Brothers/Arthur Sutherland (Box 237, Folder 1)
    Concerns insurance policies, mortgage certificates and sales, properties owned by the N-YHS, salary increases, and other financial matters.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wellenkamp, Katherine S. (Box 237, Folder 2)
    Katherine Wellenkamp served as Curator for the Thompson Memorial Homestead in East Hampton, NY. Exchanges concern the receipt of N-YHS publications The Quarterly Bulletin and Annual Reports, Wellenkemp's duties as curator, and other related matters.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wel-Wez (2 folders) (Box 237, Folder 3-4)
    Correspondent: Mrs. Jason Rogers Westerfield.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Westervelt, Leonidas (Box 237, Folder 5)
    Concerns Leonidas Westervelt discussing his Jenny Lind Collection on radio stations WEAF and WABC and the opening of the Jenny Lind exhibition.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wh (Box 237, Folder 6)
    Concerns circulars for The White & Wyckoff Art Calendar sent to Donald A. Shelley from White & Wyckoff Manufacturing Company.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Whitney Museum of American Art (Box 237, Folder 7)
    Concerns an exchange of publications with the Whitney Museum of American Art and William Sawitzky working on the catalogue of Ralph Earl as advisor on selection of material for the show. Correspondent: Juliana Force (Director).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wia-Wil (2 folders), 1942-1945 (Box 237, Folder 8-9)
    Concerns the N-YHS's subscription to the new series of The William and Mary Quarterly publication into a magazine of early American history, institutions, and culture (includes Volume 1, 1944, No. 1, Third Series)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Willoughbys (Box 237, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wills, Louis C. (Box 237, Folder 11)
    Louis C. Wills was involved with several community and social causes including serving as Vice Chairman of the American Red Cross in Brooklyn, and as Chairman of the Board on the Brooklyn Home for Children.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wim-Wiz (Box 237, Folder 12)
    Correspondents include Dr. Gilbert H. Doane (Director, General Library, University of Wisconsin) and Dr. Edward P. Alexander (Superintendent, State Historical Society of Wisconsin).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Woa-Woz (Box 237, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Wr-Wy (Box 237, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Y (Box 237, Folder 15)
    Concerns returned check to N-YHS from Yank: The Army Weekly, upon the publication of its final printing.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Yale University (Box 237, Folder 16)
    Concerns reference requests from several professors including Richard L. Purdy, Adolph B. Benson, and Donald Wing (Head, Accessions Department).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Youtz, Philip N. (Box 237, Folder 17)
    Concerns Philip N. Youtz being commissioned as Architect for the layout plans of the lots acquired by the N-YHS and the expansion of stacks to accommodate the museum's growing collections, as well as plans for the further expansion of the building to encompass an Education Building. Plans were unrealized (see also NYHS-RG 3: Guide to the New-York Historical Society Original Building Planning & Construction Records).
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Z (Box 238, Folder 1)
    Concerns retirement of Edward A. Zabriskie as Principal of the Washington Irving High School and death of William H. Zerbe, staff photographer of New York Herald Tribune.
  - Correspondence 1943-1945. Zabriskie, George A. (6 folders) (Box 238, Folder 2-7)
    Correspondence between George A. Zabriskie (President, N-YHS) and N-YHS officers including Directors A.J.Wall and R.W.G. Vail, Publications Editor Charles Baker, and others. Concerns mortgages held by the N-YHS, financial, real estate, museum and exhibition updates, Zabriskie's gifts to the Society, his article in the Bulletin concerning Ponce de Leon, research inquiries from and responses to Zabriskie (including information concerning Alderman Albert George Zabriskie and General Lafayette's visit to New York), and other matters.
  - Correspondence 1946-1947. Aa-Ak (Box 238, Folder 8)
    Concerns the funding requests for the restoration of the birthplace of Abigail Adams.
  - Correspondence 1946-1947. Addressograph (Box 238, Folder 9)
    Concerns requests for address plates for the Society from Charlotte Rowell (Secretary to Director).
  - Correspondence 1946-1947. Al (Box 238, Folder 10)
    Concerns the publishing of monograph on Connecticut painter Reuben Moulthrop, written by Mrs. William Sawitzky from notes left by her late husband. Correspondents include Lyman Allyn Museum and the Fort Palin-Nelliston Historical Society.
  - Correspondence 1946-1947. Albany Institute of History & Art (Box 238, Folder 11)
    Concerns permission from J.D. Hatch (Director, Albany Institute of History and Art) to reproduce a portrait of Jeremiah Day attributed to Reuben Moulthrop for publication in Sawitzky's monograph on Reuben Moultrop (1763-1814), prepared by Mrs. William Sawitzky (see also: John Doris Hatch, 1960).
  - Correspondence 1946-1947. Am (Box 238, Folder 12)
    Correspondents include Amherst College and Ames & Rollinson (Engrossers).
  - Correspondence 1946-1947. Ar (Box 238, Folder 13)
    Correspondents include Art in America, Art Digest, and Argosy Book Stores.
  - Correspondence 1946-1947. American Antiquarian Society (Box 239, Folder 1)
    Concerns the deposit to N-YHS of Paltsits collection of correspondence and documentary records from the Antiquarian Society as it comprised local New York material; includes key for chest that was deposited along with other materials. Correspondent: Clarence S. Brigham (Director).
  - Correspondence 1946-1947. American Association for State & Local History (Box 239, Folder 2)
    Dorothy C. Barck (Librarian, N-YHS) served as President of the American Association for State and Local History. Concerns subscription to American Heritage, and administrative issues including amendments to the Association's constitution.
  - Correspondence 1946-1947. American A- American B (Box 239, Folder 3)